ALL CHARACTERS, ORGANIZATIONS, EVENTS, AND LOCATIONS IN THIS SHOW ARE FICTITIOUS
모든 캐릭터, 조직, 이벤트, 이 쇼의 위치는 허구입니다.
Doesn't love change?
사랑은 변하지 않는가?
It did so for you.
그것은 당신을 위해 그랬습니다.
So?
그래서?
Is that why you're hanging around my wife?
그래서 당신이 내 아내 주위에 맴돌고 있는 겁니까?
So what if I am?
그렇다면 내가 그렇다면 어떨까요?
What?
무엇?
Would you look at this ******** scumbag?
이 ******** 쓰레기 좀 봐줄래?
Hey!
여기요!
Don't curse at me!
나한테 욕하지 마세요!
I called you what you deserve to be called!
내가 전화했어 당신은 무엇이라고 불릴 자격이 있습니까!
Hey, what are you two doing?
야, 둘이 뭐해?
We should be the ones fighting, not you!
싸우는 사람은 당신이 아니라 우리가 되어야 합니다!
You bastard!
이 개자식!
What are you doing? This is a hospital, you two!
뭐하세요? 여긴 병원이야, 너희 둘!
Why are you being like this?
왜 이러는 걸까요?
Don't bite him like a coward!
겁쟁이처럼 그를 물지 마세요!
You'll get hurt.
당신은 다칠 것이다.
-Your nose is bleeding!
-코피가 나네요!
Aren't you guys doctors at this hospital?
너희들은 이 병원 의사 아니냐?
That's dangerous. Don't do it!
그건 위험해요. 하지 마세요!
Professor Seo.
서 교수님.
-This is a hospital! -Wait.
-여기는 병원이에요! -기다리다.
-You two must be crazy! -Come on!
-너희 둘은 미쳤나봐! -어서 해봐요!
Can't you see you're in a hospital?
병원에 있는 거 안보여?
-This is all your fault. -Do you want to get hit?
-이건 다 네 잘못이야. -맞고 싶나요?
-Let go.
- 놔.
-I'll hit you twice. -Three times.
- 두 번 때릴게요. - 세 번.
-Do you want to be hit four times? -This is all your fault.
- 네 번 맞고 싶나요? -이건 다 네 잘못이야.
This is all your fault!
이건 다 네 잘못이야!
Let go of my hair!
내 머리카락을 놔줘!
All of you, stop!
여러분, 그만하세요!
My back.
내 등.
We were fighting because of Bong-suk, but why were you two…
봉석이 때문에 싸웠는데 그런데 너희 둘은 왜...?
Have you two lost it?
두 분은 잃어버리셨나요?
Is this how you should act in a hospital?
병원에서는 이렇게 행동해야 하나요?
What's with you? I thought you were all about maintaining your image.
당신은 무엇입니까? 나는 당신이 그럴 줄 알았는데 이미지 유지에 관한 모든 것.
Have you completely lost your mind?
완전히 정신을 잃었나요?
Dr. Kim, you too.
김박사님, 당신도 마찬가지입니다.
There are already rumors about how we're in a love triangle.
벌써 소문이 나네요 우리가 어떻게 삼각관계에 있는지에 대해.
Are you trying to give people more things to gossip about?
사람들에게 더 많은 것을 주려고 하시나요? 험담하려고?
How could the two of you be so thoughtless and immature?
어떻게 너희 둘이 그럴 수 있지? 너무 생각이 없고 철없어?
How could you lose control of your emotions and let this happen?
어떻게 통제력을 잃을 수 있니? 당신의 감정을 무시하고 이런 일이 일어나도록 하시겠습니까?
Dr. Cha, I'm sorry. I have no excuses to give.
차 박사님, 죄송합니다. 변명의 여지가 없습니다.
We'll just say that we fought because we don't get along.
그냥 싸웠다고 하자 왜냐하면 우리는 사이가 좋지 않기 때문입니다.
-Are you serious? You're the one who-- -Enough!
- 진심이에요? 당신은 바로 그 사람이-- -충분해요!
But why are you sleeping in someone else's house?
그런데 왜 자고 있는 거야? 다른 사람 집에?
You should be embarrassed.
부끄러워해야합니다.
Why should I be embarrassed? For what?
내가 왜 부끄러워해야 합니까? 무엇을 위해?
There are others too.
다른 사람들도 있습니다.
Dr. Jeon and Chief Resident Hwang are there too.
전 박사와 황 원장 거기에도 있어요.
I guess you only see indecent things.
음란한 것만 보는 것 같아요.
What on earth are you imagining?
도대체 무슨 상상을 하고 있는 걸까요?
Thanks for bringing it up. What do you think?
제기해 주셔서 감사합니다. 어떻게 생각하나요?
Put yourself in my shoes.
내 입장이 되어보세요.
That isn't possible. I never cheated on anyone in the first place.
그것은 불가능합니다. 난 속인 적 없어 우선 누구에게나.
And I don't have a secret love child.
그리고 나에게는 비밀스러운 사랑의 아이가 없습니다.
Come here, you *******! Damn it!
이리와, 이 개자식아! 젠장!
For goodness' sake!
세상에!
You dodged my blow? You little…
내 공격을 피했나요? 너 좀…
Jeez.
이런.
Calm down.
진정하다.
It hurts.
아파요.
Come on, why are you pushing yourself like this?
어서, 왜 밀고 있어? 너도 이렇지?
GUSAN UNIVERSITY HOSPITAL
구산대학교병원
The baby is being discharged tomorrow.
아기는 내일 퇴원합니다.
Really? That's great.
정말? 훌륭해요.
-Did you think of a name yet? -Li-ji.
-아직 이름을 생각하지 않았나요? -리지.
"Li-ji"?
"리지"?
Short for "Little Ji-seon."
'리틀지선'의 줄임말.
I heard it's a trend to use English-sounding names.
사용하는 추세라고 들었는데 영어로 들리는 이름.
-The baby is pretty, right? -Yes, she's so pretty.
-아기가 예쁘죠? -네, 너무 예뻐요.
She already looks at me, and sometimes she even smiles.
그 사람은 벌써 나를 보고 있고, 때로는 웃기도 합니다.
But I heard that's not a real smile, just some kind of reflex.
그런데 그건 진짜 미소가 아니라고 들었는데, 그냥 일종의 반사작용일 뿐이에요.
She's so cute.
그녀는 너무 귀여워요.
What's wrong? Are you in pain?
무슨 일이야? 고통스럽나요?
Yes. My stomach keeps hurting.
예. 배가 계속 아프네요.
-Maybe it's time for me to die. -Don't say things like that.
- 어쩌면 이제 죽을 시간이 된 것 같아요. - 그런 말은 하지 마세요.
Go to the ER, okay?
응급실로 가세요, 알았죠?
Can't you just take a look?
그냥 좀 봐주시면 안 될까요?
Well, that wouldn't be right.
글쎄요, 그건 옳지 않습니다.
Then go to the Family Medicine Department and get examined there, okay?
그럼 가정의학과로 가세요 그리고 거기서 검사를 받아요, 알았죠?
Which professor is doing outpatient appointments today again?
어느 교수님이 하시는지 오늘 또 외래 진료 예약이야?
-Does your stomach hurt a lot? -It's better than before.
-배가 많이 아프나요? - 예전보다 좋아졌어요.
It hasn't been long since you've given birth,
오래되지 않았어 당신이 출산한 이후로,
so even a small symptom can progress to a serious illness.
그래서 작은 증상이라도 심각한 질병으로 발전할 수 있습니다.
I see.
알겠어요.
And I am worried since you have an issue with your colon as well.
그리고 당신이 그랬기 때문에 나는 걱정됩니다 결장에도 문제가 있습니다.
I think it might be an intestinal obstruction.
내 생각엔 그럴 수도 있을 것 같아 장폐색.
I think you should be admitted and monitored.
내 생각엔 네가 입학해야 할 것 같아 그리고 모니터링했습니다.
Admitted?
인정됐나요?
Don't be so obvious.
너무 뻔하게 말하지 마세요.
Finish your job before you collapse.
쓰러지기 전에 일을 끝내세요.
Seo Jung-min speaking.
서정민이 말하고 있다.
Yes, I'll go there right away.
네, 바로 거기로 갈게요.
Are you okay?
괜찮으세요?
My baby is being discharged tomorrow. We have to go home together.
우리 아기가 내일 퇴원해요. 우리는 함께 집에 가야 해요.
Then you should have said that you didn't want to be admitted.
그럼 이렇게 말했어야지 당신이 인정받기를 원하지 않았다는 것입니다.
The doctor said she should be admitted, and she agreed to it on impulse.
의사가 입원해야 한다고 하더군요. 그리고 그녀는 충동적으로 그것에 동의했습니다.
Doctor, please let me be discharged.
박사님, 퇴원하게 해주세요.
Our professor requested a consultation with the Surgery Department.
교수님께서 상담을 요청하셨습니다 외과부와 함께.
We'll hear what the doctor there has to say before discharging you.
거기 의사가 뭐라고 하는지 들어보자 당신을 퇴원시키기 전에 말해야 합니다.
He's here.
그는 여기 있습니다.
Dr. Seo, you came?
서박사님 오셨나요?
Hello.
안녕하세요.
Yes, it is that patient.
응, 그 환자야.
She came to Family Medicine due to abdominal pain.
가정의학과에 오셨어요 복통으로 인해.
She has symptoms of nausea and vomiting.
메스꺼움과 구토 증상이 있습니다.
It's not severe, and she has bowel movements.
심하진 않은데, 그리고 그녀는 배변을 합니다.
Rebound?
리바운드?
It's kind of borderline.
일종의 경계선이죠.
It doesn't seem like appendicitis
맹장염은 아닌거 같은데
or a symptom related to the colon.
또는 결장과 관련된 증상.
And I suspect there might be a little ileus.
그리고 나는 의심한다 약간의 장폐색이 있을 수 있습니다.
Okay.
좋아요.
Then I'll give her that explanation and discharge her.
그럼 내가 그 사람한테 설명해줄게 그리고 그녀를 퇴원시킵니다.
There's a condition called acute abdomen.
급성 복부라는 질환이 있습니다.
It occurs when the stomach or intestines rupture and peritonitis occurs.
위장이나 장에 이상이 있을 때 발생합니다. 파열 및 복막염이 발생합니다.
Your symptoms right now aren't exactly acute abdomen symptoms,
지금 당신의 증상은 그렇지 않습니다. 정확히는 급성 복부 증상,
but we can't rule out the possibility either.
하지만 우리는 배제할 수 없어 가능성도.
The professor wants you to be admitted if possible,
교수님이 당신을 원해요 가능하다면 입학을 허가하고,
or at the very least take a CT scan to check things.
아니면 최소한 가져가세요 사물을 확인하기 위해 CT 스캔.
There's a possibility your abdominal symptoms will worsen
가능성이 있어요 복부 증상이 악화될 것입니다
if you leave the hospital.
병원을 떠나면.
If peritonitis or perforation in your stomach or intestines occurs,
복막염이나 천공이 발생한 경우 위장이나 장에 발생하며,
then it might be difficult to perform surgery.
그러면 어려울 수도 있겠네요 수술을 하려고.
But if you insist on going home, you should skip a few meals.
하지만 집에 가려고 고집한다면, 식사를 몇 번 건너뛰어야 합니다.
If your condition improves, you can have food that's easy to digest.
상태가 좋아지면, 소화하기 쉬운 음식을 먹을 수 있습니다.
And always keep your stomach warm.
그리고 항상 배를 따뜻하게 유지하세요.
Okay, I'll do that.
알았어, 그렇게 할게요.
It's natural that a cancer patient feels pain sometimes.
암환자라면 당연한 일 가끔 통증을 느낀다.
-Bye. -But, Dr. Seo,
-안녕. -근데 서 박사님,
are you sick?
너 아프니?
You look sicker than I do.
당신이 나보다 더 아파 보이는군요.
I'm fine.
잘 지내요.
Dr. Seo, do you want to see a picture of my baby?
서 박사님, 보실래요? 내 아기 사진?
She's adorable.
그녀는 사랑스럽다.
MOCK EXAM RESULTS
모의고사 결과
I took all my stuff from the art academy.
나는 미술학원에서 모든 것을 가져왔다.
Get a refund on the fees for this month.
이번 달 수수료를 환불 받으세요.
The rounds are done, right? You all can go.
라운드는 끝났죠? 모두 갈 수 있습니다.
Dr. Cha, can I have a word?
차 박사님, 한마디 해도 될까요?
When will you decide?
언제 결정하실 건가요?
-What? -You need to decide
-무엇? - 결정해야 해
whether you'll get a divorce or not so I can plan my next move.
이혼할지 말지 그래서 다음 행보를 계획할 수 있어요.
-You must have lost your mind. -No, I'm completely fine.
-정신을 잃었나 봐요. -아니요, 저는 전혀 괜찮아요.
My feelings are clearer now than ever before.
내 감정이 더 선명해졌어 지금은 그 어느 때보다.
I hate seeing you.
나는 당신을 만나는 것이 싫어요.
It's annoying to see you at the hospital every day,
짜증나 매일 병원에서 만나요
to the point of driving me crazy.
나를 미치게 만들 정도로.
So hurry up and leave.
그러니 서둘러서 떠나세요.
Choi Seung-hi.
최승희.
Are you really the impressive woman I used to know?
정말로요? 내가 알던 인상적인 여자?
I'm disappointed because I thought you'd be different.
나는 실망했다 왜냐하면 나는 당신이 다를 것이라고 생각했기 때문입니다.
Were you always this low and vulgar?
당신은 항상 이렇게 천박하고 천박했습니까?
I'm doing this to avoid being low and vulgar.
나는 이것을 피하기 위해 이것을하고 있습니다 낮고 천박하다.
Ever since you began working here,
당신이 여기서 일하기 시작한 이후로,
I had to live in silence like a sinner whenever I saw you.
죄인처럼 묵묵히 살아야만 했어 당신을 볼 때마다.
But I won't live like that anymore
하지만 난 더 이상 그렇게 살지 않을 거야
and I won't stand my daughter being treated like some sinner too.
그리고 난 내 딸을 참지 않을 거야 죄인 취급을 받기도 합니다.
You've got to be kidding me.
지금 농담하고 계시군요.
So this is how you act despite being aware that you are a sinner?
그래서 이렇게 행동하는구나 당신이 죄인인 것을 알면서도?
Sure, thanks for bringing this up.
물론이죠. 이 문제를 제기해 주셔서 감사합니다.
During college, when I got pregnant and married In-ho,
대학 시절, 임신했을 때 인호와 결혼했고,
you…
당신은…
looked at me with such loathing until we graduated.
나를 그렇게 혐오스러운 눈으로 바라보았어 우리가 졸업할 때까지.
You disregarded me and looked at me with such disdain that it was humiliating.
넌 나를 무시하고 쳐다봤지 굴욕적일 정도로 경멸적으로.
You didn't allow me to forget my wrongdoing until we graduated.
넌 내가 잊는 걸 허락하지 않았어 졸업할 때까지 내 잘못은.
But you find it unfair that you were treated like a sinner for a few months?
하지만 당신은 당신이 그랬다는 것이 불공평하다고 생각합니다 몇 달 동안 죄인 취급을 받았나요?
Are you that angry that your daughter has to start college a year late?
딸이 그렇게 화가 났나요? 대학을 1년 늦게 시작해야 하나요?
This doesn't make things fair.
이것은 일을 공평하게 만들지 않습니다.
Sure, if you don't want to quit, keep working here.
물론, 그만두고 싶지 않다면 여기서 계속 일하세요.
But in return,
하지만 그 대가로,
while I'm receiving my training,
제가 훈련을 받는 동안,
you'll have a constant reminder of what you've done
계속해서 알림을 받게 될 거예요 당신이 한 일 중
every time you look at my face.
네가 내 얼굴을 볼 때마다.
Then can I take back what's mine?
그러면 내 것을 다시 가져갈 수 있나요?
The happy family you maintained for over 20 years,
당신이 지켜준 행복한 가족 20년 넘게,
the very thing you stole from me?
당신이 나에게서 훔친 바로 그것?
You lunatic.
이 미치광이.
Watch what you say. I'm your advisor.
당신이 말하는 것을 조심하세요. 나는 당신의 조언자입니다.
-Know your place. -How unfortunate.
-당신의 위치를 ​​알아라. -정말 불행한 일이군요.
That's all you can say to me now, right?
지금 나한테 할 수 있는 말은 그게 다야, 그렇지?
Right?
오른쪽?
Is your goal to torture me? Or is it Seo In-ho?
나를 고문하려는 목적인가요? 아니면 서인호인가?
I don't have to explain anything to you.
나는 당신에게 아무것도 설명할 필요가 없습니다.
Stop dragging this out and decide.
이제 그만 끌고 결정하세요.
I already said this, but I'm not quitting this hospital.
나는 이미 이렇게 말했습니다. 하지만 난 이 병원을 그만둘 생각은 없어요.
So if anything, you quit.
그러니 무슨 일이 있어도 그만두세요.
Or expose everything and see what will happen afterward!
아니면 다 노출시키던가 그리고 나중에 무슨 일이 일어날지 지켜보세요!
Aren't you even curious about Eun-seo?
은서의 모습도 궁금하지 않나요?
She'll probably fail to go to college this year!
그 사람은 아마 실패할 거야 올해 대학에 가려고!
She can't draw and she quit her academy.
그녀는 그림을 그릴 수 없어 학원을 그만뒀다.
And they don't know how long it'll take for her to recover!
그리고 그들은 얼마나 오래 걸릴지 모릅니다 그녀가 회복하는 데 시간이 걸릴 거예요!
Say something!
뭐라고 말해보세요!
Is that why you went to Jeong-suk?
그래서 정숙이한테 간 거야?
Yes, and I'm not quitting this hospital.
네, 그리고 저는 이 병원을 그만둘 생각이 없습니다.
If she can't take it, she should leave instead of me.
만약 그녀가 그것을 참을 수 없다면, 그 사람이 나 대신 떠나야 해.
I'm not backing down anymore. I'm getting back what was mine.
나는 더 이상 물러서지 않을 것이다. 나는 내 것이었던 것을 돌려받는다.
Why? Can I not?
왜? 나는 할 수 없습니까?
Can't I just have a regular family?
그냥 평범한 가족을 가질 수는 없나요?
Does Eun-seo have to live without a father forever?
은서는 살아야 하는가? 영원히 아버지 없이?
Seung-hi, I don't know if this is right.
승희야, 이게 맞는지 모르겠어.
Looking at how things turned out,
상황이 어떻게 되었는지 살펴보면,
we could be fated for each other.
우리는 서로의 운명을 가질 수 있습니다.
Let's talk after work.
퇴근 후에 얘기하자.
EMERGENCY MEDICAL CENTER
응급 의료 센터
Excuse me, please show me Yoo Ji-seon's CT scan.
죄송합니다. 보여주세요. 유지선의 CT촬영.
Gosh.
이런.
This is a report about a patient in the ER.
보고서입니다 응급실에 있는 환자에 대해.
She is a 21-year-old woman with whole abdomen DT and RT.
21세 여성입니다 복부 전체 DT 및 RT.
Her WBC is up to 18,000, her hemoglobin is up to 8.5,
그녀의 WBC는 최대 18,000이고, 그녀의 헤모글로빈 수치는 최대 8.5입니다.
and her CRP is up to 56 according to her labs.
그녀의 CRP는 최대 56입니다. 그녀의 연구실에 따르면.
And free air has been observed in her chest PA.
그리고 자유 공기가 관찰되었습니다 그녀의 가슴 PA에.
The CT scan shows perforation of a gastric ulcer
CT 스캔 결과 위궤양 천공
and a lot of fluid buildup in her peritoneum and bowel material soiling.
그리고 액체가 많이 쌓였습니다. 복막과 장 물질이 오염되었습니다.
Shouldn't you report this to the Gastrointestinal Surgery Department?
이거 신고하면 안되는거냐 소화기외과?
Most of the professors are at a conference and thus out of office.
대부분의 교수들이 회의에 참석하고 있습니다. 따라서 부재 중입니다.
And the ones remaining are in the middle of surgeries.
그리고 남은 것들은 수술 중이에요.
You're the professor on duty today,
오늘 당번 교수님이시군요
I came to you because it was so urgent.
너무 급한 일이라 찾아왔습니다.
Her vitals?
그녀의 바이탈?
Her BP is 90 over 50, and heart rate is 105.
그녀의 혈압은 50에 90이고, 심박수는 105입니다.
Her fever is at 38.1°.
발열은 38.1°입니다.
-Is a vasopressor agent being used? -Yes, a central line was inserted
- 혈관수축제를 사용하고 있나요? - 네 중앙선이 삽입됐어요
to administer a low dosage of dopamine.
저용량의 도파민을 투여합니다.
And she's been given 500cc of fluid.
그리고 수액 500cc를 주었어요.
What's the patient's name?
환자의 이름은 무엇입니까?
Yoo Ji-seon.
유지선.
Get an anesthesiologist, secure an OR, and get a consent form.
마취과 의사를 구하고, 수술실을 확보하고, 그리고 동의서를 받아요.
Warn the guardians about the situation.
보호자에게 상황을 알립니다.
I'll go straight to the OR.
바로 수술실로 가겠습니다.
Okay, thank you.
알겠습니다. 감사합니다.
Jeez, the smell.
이런, 냄새.
It was like this for longer than I thought.
이랬어 생각보다 오랫동안.
The lesions are too severe for an ulcer.
궤양이라기에는 병변이 너무 심합니다.
Isn't this perforated cancer?
이거 천공암 아닌가요?
I can feel small nodules on her abdominal wall.
작은 결절이 느껴지네요 그녀의 복벽에.
I think it's peritoneal seeding.
복막 파종인 것 같아요.
Isn't this a patient with colon cancer that metastasized to the liver?
이 사람 대장암 환자 아닌가요? 간으로 전이됐나요?
Has it metastasized to the stomach?
위장으로 전이됐나요?
Rather than metastasis to the stomach,
위장으로의 전이보다는
it's a gastric cancer perforation with peritoneal seeding.
위암 천공이야 복막 파종으로.
Then it is a double primary cancer?
그렇다면 이중원발암인가요?
We'll need to do a biopsy to be sure.
확실하게 하려면 생체검사를 해야 합니다.
The situation is really bad, but let's give it a shot.
상황이 정말 안좋습니다, 하지만 한번 시도해 봅시다.
Prepare a lot of warm saline irrigation.
따뜻한 식염수 관개를 많이 준비하십시오.
Contact the Pathology Department for a biopsy.
병리과에 문의하세요 생체검사를 위해.
Okay.
좋아요.
Have you eaten?
식사하셨나요?
Like you even care.
당신이 신경 쓰는 것처럼.
Choi Seung-hi said I should quit and divorce you.
최승희가 말했다. 그만두고 이혼해야겠어요.
She seemed to want to settle down with you.
그녀는 원하는 것 같았다 당신과 함께 정착하기 위해.
Do you feel the same?
당신도 같은 느낌이 드나요?
Would you two be happy if I bow out?
내가 절하면 너희 둘은 행복할까?
What are you on about? I have no intention of doing that.
지금 무슨 일을 하고 계시나요? 나는 그렇게 할 생각이 없습니다.
I don't care.
나는 상관하지 않는다.
I don't care if you two settle down or not.
난 상관없어 너희 둘이 정착하든 안 하든.
Just don't get on my nerves.
내 신경을 건드리지 마세요.
Don't drive me crazier than I already am.
지금보다 더 나를 미치게 만들지 마세요.
Give me some time.
시간을 좀 주세요.
I'll end things.
이만 마치겠습니다.
Seung-hi, I have something to say.
승희 씨, 할 말이 있어요.
Say it. Just don't say that we should break up.
말해 보세요. 그냥 말하지마 우리 헤어져야 한다고.
If you say that, I'm going to kill you.
그렇게 말하면 죽여버리겠다.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
I really have no words.
정말 말이 없어요.
Shut up.
입 다물어.
I'll do my best for Eun-seo.
은서를 위해 최선을 다하겠습니다.
But I need to go back…
하지만 돌아가야 해요…
to where I belong.
내가 속한 곳으로.
My life went off track because of my own mistakes,
내 인생은 궤도를 벗어났어 내 자신의 실수 때문에
but I think it's time to set things right.
하지만 이제 상황을 바로잡을 때가 된 것 같아요.
I don't think I'll get another chance.
다시는 기회가 없을 것 같아요.
I know this is cruel to you, and I'm so sorry.
나는 이것이 당신에게 잔인하다는 것을 알고 있습니다. 정말 미안해요.
But this could be the best for you too.
하지만 이것이 당신에게도 최선일 수 있습니다.
Think of it like that.
그렇게 생각해보세요.
You're…
당신은…
abandoning me again?
또 나를 버리고?
You can live a better life without me.
나 없이도 당신은 더 나은 삶을 살 수 있습니다.
You're the only one who doesn't see that like a fool.
당신은 유일한 사람입니다 그것을 바보처럼 보지 않는 사람.
Why are you deciding that for me?
왜 나를 위해 그걸 결정하는 거야?
Do you know how lonely I was this whole time?
당신은 알고 있나요 그동안 얼마나 외로웠지?
Do you really not know how much Eun-seo
은서가 얼마나 많은지 정말 모르시나요?
needs a father?
아버지가 필요해?
Even if you go back,
돌아가더라도,
you won't be treated like you were before.
당신은 이전처럼 대우받지 못할 것입니다.
They'll be hard on you until the day you die.
그들은 당신을 힘들게 할 거예요 죽는 날까지.
I know.
알아요.
But you are still going back?
그런데 아직도 돌아가는 거야?
Do you love your wife?
당신은 아내를 사랑합니까?
I…
나는…
rely on her a lot.
그녀에게 많이 의지하세요.
When I think about it,
생각해보면,
I depended on her a lot when we had the kids
나는 그녀에게 많이 의지했다 우리가 아이들을 가졌을 때
at such a young age
그렇게 어린 나이에
and when my father was sick.
그리고 아버지가 아팠을 때.
So I want to spend the rest of my life
그래서 나는 남은 인생을 보내고 싶다.
asking for her forgiveness.
그녀에게 용서를 구합니다.
So now you're saying you've depended on your wife?
그럼 지금 당신이 말하는 건 당신은 아내에게 의존해왔나요?
Ask for forgiveness?
용서를 구하나요?
If you had any conscience, you wouldn't say that.
양심이 있었다면, 당신은 그렇게 말하지 않을 것입니다.
You don't have a right to be saying those things.
당신은 권리가 없습니다 그런 말을 하게 되는 거죠.
If things end between us, I'll be the one to end them.
우리 사이의 일이 끝난다면, 나는 그들을 끝내는 사람이 될 것입니다.
If you say something like this again,
또 이런 말 하면
it'll be me who exposes everything, not your wife.
모든 걸 폭로하는 건 나일 거야 당신 아내가 아닙니다.
-Do you understand? -Seung-hi.
-이해했나요? -승희.
Don't be so obstinate.
너무 고집하지 마세요.
You horrible bastard.
이 끔찍한 놈.
You cowardly jerk.
이 겁쟁이 멍청이.
You piece of trash.
너 쓰레기야.
-Hello, Doctor. -Hello.
-안녕하세요, 박사님. -안녕하세요.
What is it?
그것은 무엇입니까?
Tell me in detail.
자세히 말해 보세요.
Are you here for Jung-min?
정민씨 찾으러 오셨나요?
He's not at work and he's not answering his phone.
그 사람은 직장에 없어요 그런데 그 사람이 전화를 안 받네요.
I came here thinking he might be home.
그 사람이 집에 있을지도 모른다고 생각하고 여기로 왔어요.
-What about Mother? -She's not here.
- 어머니는요? - 그녀는 여기 없어요.
I-rang isn't back from her academy.
아이랑이 학원에서 돌아오지 않았어요.
How weak of him.
그 사람은 얼마나 약한가.
How dare he try to hide instead of fixing this mess?
그 사람이 어떻게 감히 숨기려고 합니까? 이 엉망진창을 고치는 대신?
This isn't the time to be saying that.
지금은 그런 말을 할 때가 아니다.
I'm just upset, that's all!
그냥 속상할 뿐이야, 그게 다야!
Yes, hello.
네, 안녕하세요.
Hello, ma'am.
안녕하세요, 부인.
Did you know that I-rang's mock exam grades have come out?
그것을 알고 계셨나요? 아이랑 모의고사 성적 나왔나요?
Yes.
그렇습니다.
But I haven't been able to check them yet.
하지만 아직 확인해 보지는 못했습니다.
Her national rank fell by a lot this time around.
국가 순위가 하락했습니다. 이번에는 많이 늘었습니다.
And I-rang is feeling very discouraged.
그리고 아이랑은 매우 낙담한 상태입니다.
And on top of that…
그리고 게다가…
Yes.
그렇습니다.
Yes, of course.
물론이죠.
Yes, okay.
응, 알았어.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
Was that I-rang's homeroom teacher?
그 아이랑 담임 선생님이셨어요?
What did she say?
그녀가 뭐라고 말했습니까?
Her mock exam grades fell by a lot.
모의고사 성적이 많이 떨어졌어요.
See, I knew this would happen!
봐, 난 이런 일이 일어날 줄 알았어!
She slacked off now that she's pursuing art.
그녀는 느슨해졌어 이제 그녀는 예술을 추구하고 있습니다.
I told you she shouldn't slack off even if she changes her academic path!
내가 말했잖아, 그 사람이 게으름 피우면 안 된다고 그녀가 진로를 바꾸더라도!
Whose fault is this?
이건 누구의 잘못인가요?
I-rang doesn't talk at school lately.
이랑이는 요즘 학교에서 말을 안 해요.
The teacher asked me if something is going on at home.
선생님이 나한테 물으셨어 집에 무슨 일이 생기면.
Do you not understand what caused all this?
이해가 안 가시나요? 이 모든 일의 원인은 무엇입니까?
There's no time for this. Get changed.
이럴 시간이 없습니다. 갈아입으세요.
We have to go somewhere.
우리는 어딘가로 가야 해요.
I am so deeply sorry for your loss.
당신의 상실에 대해 매우 유감스럽게 생각합니다.
The doctor who neglected my daughter is your son, is he not?
내 딸을 방치한 의사 당신 아들이요, 아닌가요?
How come you two are here instead of your son who killed my child?
왜 너희 둘이 여기 있니? 내 아이를 죽인 네 아들 대신에?
You thought you could leave her to die just because she was terminally ill?
당신은 그녀를 죽게 내버려 둘 수 있다고 생각했어요 단지 그녀가 불치병에 걸렸기 때문에?
This is medical malpractice!
이것은 의료 과실이다!
I'm going to sue all of you!
너희 모두를 고소할 거야!
I'm going to sue you and see that you all go to jail!
나는 당신을 고소 할 것입니다 그리고 너희 모두 감옥에 가는 걸 지켜봐라!
Enough, stop it.
이제 그만하세요.
Ji-seon can hear you.
지선이가 들을 수 있어요.
I'm saying it so she does hear me!
내가 이렇게 말하는 건 그 사람이 내 말을 듣게 하기 위함이에요!
How can you discharge a sick patient without saying a word to her guardian?
아픈 환자를 어떻게 퇴원시킬 수 있나요? 보호자에게 한마디도 하지 않고?
This is clearly medical malpractice. Take responsibility!
이는 명백한 의료 과실입니다. 책임을 져라!
Gosh, I feel so bad for our Ji-seon. What do we do?
맙소사, 우리 지선이가 너무 불쌍해요. 우리는 무엇을 합니까?
How shameless of you to come!
당신이 오다니 얼마나 뻔뻔한 일입니까!
Bring that doctor here right now!
지금 당장 그 의사를 여기로 데려오세요!
Gosh, our poor Ji-seon.
맙소사, 우리 불쌍한 지선이.
How will you take responsibility for what happened to Ji-seon?
어떻게 책임을 질 것인가? 지선이한테 무슨 일이 있었던 걸까요?
How?
어떻게?
Don't just sit there, say something!
거기 그냥 앉아 있지 말고 뭐라고 말이라도 해보세요!
-What do we do for our poor Ji-seon? -Darn it.
-불쌍한 우리 지선이를 위해 우리는 무엇을 해줄까? -젠장.
SEO JUNG-MIN
서정민
-Dr. Jeon. -Yes?
-박사. 전. -예?
The patient Hong Seo-hui wants to see you because her pain is severe.
환자 홍서휘가 보고싶다 왜냐하면 그녀의 고통이 심하기 때문입니다.
Okay, I'll go there now.
알았어, 지금 거기로 갈게.
Dr. Jeon, I saw Dr. Seo Jung-min earlier.
전 박사님, 아까 서정민 박사님을 뵈었습니다.
Where?
어디?
Family Medicine requested
가정의학을 요청함
a consultation with our department regarding that patient, right?
우리 부서와 상담 그 환자에 관해서는 그렇죠?
When was that?
그게 언제였나요?
The day she was discharged.
그녀가 퇴원한 날.
Who was the doctor in charge?
담당 의사는 누구였나요?
A third-year named Park Ji-yeon. She's our chief resident.
3학년 박지연. 그녀는 우리의 주요 거주자입니다.
-Why? -I'm just checking the facts.
-왜? - 사실관계만 확인 중이에요.
We need to check who should be held accountable.
우리는 확인해야합니다 책임을 져야 할 사람.
Your department might've misdiagnosed her in the first place.
당신의 부서는 아마도 처음에 그녀를 잘못 진단했습니다.
Did you see the chart?
차트를 보셨나요?
I did.
그랬어요.
We asked General Surgery to take a look before discharging her.
우리는 일반외과에 진료를 요청했습니다 그녀를 퇴원하기 전에.
And Jung-min came and said she could be discharged.
그리고 정민이가 왔어요 그리고 퇴원할 수 있다고 하더군요.
I know this hurts, but Jung-min is at fault here.
난 이게 아픈 걸 알아, 그런데 여기서는 정민이 잘못이 있다.
At the very least, tests should have been run.
최소한, 테스트를 실행했어야 합니다.
So why are you talking about accountability?
그럼 왜 얘기하는 거야? 책임에 대해?
Still, we need to make it so that this was a mistake by your department.
그래도 우리는 그렇게 만들어야 해 이건 당신 부서의 실수였어요.
So that the worst won't happen to Jung-min.
최악의 상황이 발생하지 않도록 정민에게.
Choi Seung-hi was in charge.
최승희가 맡았다.
If you keep making an issue of this,
계속해서 이런 문제를 제기한다면,
Seung-hi might become embroiled in this too.
승희가 될 수도 있다 이 일에도 가담했다.
I broke up with Seung-hi.
나 승희랑 헤어졌어.
As if.
마치.
To be exact, we're in the middle of breaking up.
정확히 말하면, 우리는 헤어지는 중이야.
I'll resolve Jung-min's predicament, so don't worry.
정민이의 고민을 해결해 드리겠습니다. 그러니 걱정하지 마세요.
And if you do break up?
그리고 만약 헤어진다면?
That makes it okay to do this to her?
그렇다면 그녀에게 이런 짓을 해도 괜찮을까요?
This is for my son.
이건 내 아들을 위한 거예요.
This is hilarious.
정말 재밌네요.
Why do I suddenly feel bad for Seung-hi?
왜 갑자기 승희가 안쓰럽지?
I can't just sit back and watch Jung-min hit rock bottom.
가만히 앉아서 지켜볼 수만은 없어 정민은 바닥을 쳤다.
So don't say anything.
그러니 아무 말도 하지 마세요.
They found Jung-min.
정민이를 찾았어요.
I'll take care of I-rang.
아이랑은 내가 처리할게.
You go meet with Jung-min and make him come to his senses.
정민 만나러 가세요 그리고 그 사람이 정신을 차리게 만드세요.
Right now, Jung-min needs you
지금 정민에겐 네가 필요해
more than he needs me.
그 사람이 나를 필요로 하는 것보다 더 많이요.
What about us?
우리는 어떻습니까?
What's going to happen to us?
우리에게 무슨 일이 일어날까요?
Jeong-suk.
정숙.
Can't you forgive me?
나를 용서할 수 없나요?
MAY YOU REST IN PEACE
편히 쉬시길 바랍니다
THE LATE YOO JI-SEON
故 유지선
Before…
전에…
I started my residency,
레지던트를 시작했는데,
I almost died from acute liver failure.
나는 급성 간부전으로 거의 죽을 뻔했습니다.
I was so bitter about almost dying,
죽을 뻔 했을 정도로 너무 괴로워서,
so I can't even imagine the pain you are in…
그래서 상상도 못해요 당신이 겪고 있는 고통은…
after losing your own child.
자신의 아이를 잃은 후.
I think
내 생각엔
I might know why Ji-seon wanted to give birth to her baby…
지선이 왜 그랬는지 알겠다 아기를 낳고 싶었는데…
so badly.
너무 나쁘게.
So her mom and dad wouldn't be lonely.
그러면 엄마, 아빠가 외롭지 않을 거예요.
So they wouldn't give up on life.
그래서 그들은 삶을 포기하지 않을 것입니다.
It was her own method
그것은 그녀만의 방식이었다
of providing her parents a way
그녀의 부모에게 길을 제공하는 것
to continue to live through her child.
그녀의 아이를 통해 계속 살기 위해.
Ji-seon…
지선…
always seemed like she knew that
그녀는 항상 그걸 알고 있는 것 같았어
she was going to leave like this one day.
그녀는 언젠가 이렇게 떠날 예정이었다.
So please understand her wishes.
그러니 그녀의 바람을 이해해주세요.
Live happily with the angel your daughter left behind.
천사와 함께 행복하게 살아요 당신의 딸이 남겨졌습니다.
And…
그리고…
later on,
나중에,
you'll meet her again.
당신은 그녀를 다시 만날 것입니다.
Why…
왜…
aren't you asking me to forgive your son?
나한테 네 아들을 용서해달라고 하는 건 아니지?
I don't have the right to ask you that.
나는 당신에게 그런 질문을 할 권리가 없습니다.
ACCESSIBLE PARKING
접근 가능한 주차
DRIVER WITH DISABILITY
장애가 있는 운전자
Did you apply for your disability rating yet?
신청하셨나요? 아직 장애 등급을 확인하지 않으셨나요?
Disability rating?
장애등급?
But what's the point? There aren't many benefits.
하지만 요점은 무엇입니까? 혜택이 많지 않습니다.
What are you talking about? With parking so difficult these days,
무슨 얘기를 하는 건가요? 요즘 주차가 너무 힘들어서
it's great to park in a disabled parking space.
주차하기 너무 좋아요 장애인 주차 공간에서.
The spot is great too.
그 자리도 훌륭해요.
Jeong-suk can't come today.
정숙이는 오늘 못 온다.
I know.
알아요.
You know, and yet you keep looking around thinking she might show up.
알면서도 계속 주위를 둘러보는 너 그녀가 나타날 수도 있다고 생각합니다.
What?
무엇?
-Well… -If you don't have plans today,
-글쎄… - 오늘 계획이 없다면,
how about an afternoon drink after the run?
오후에 한잔 어때요? 실행 후?
This is about the time when our true selves need to come out.
이때쯤이야 우리의 진정한 모습이 드러나야 할 때.
I'm all about give and take.
나는주고받는 것에 관한 것입니다.
With that in mind, I'll tell you a secret.
그 점을 염두에 두고 한 가지 비밀을 말씀드리겠습니다.
But can I ask you something in return?
그런데 답례로 뭔가 물어봐도 될까요?
Okay.
좋아요.
You're good-looking.
당신은 잘 생겼어요.
I've actually run a full marathon.
실제로 풀마라톤을 완주한 적이 있어요.
I finished nine of them. You didn't know, right?
그 중 9개를 마쳤어요. 당신은 몰랐죠?
You probably had no idea.
아마 당신은 전혀 몰랐을 것입니다.
I acted my heart out if I do say so myself.
나는 진심을 다해 행동했다 내가 직접 그렇게 말한다면.
Okay, your turn.
좋아, 당신 차례야.
Do you like Jeong-suk?
정숙이를 좋아해요?
But I already knew you completed a full marathon.
하지만 난 이미 알고 있었어 당신은 풀 마라톤을 완주했습니다.
Your posture and breathing were too stable.
당신의 자세 호흡이 너무 안정적이었습니다.
Darn it.
젠장.
Then I'll tell you a different secret.
그럼 다른 비밀을 알려드릴게요.
I joined this crew because I was interested in you.
나는 이 크루에 합류했다 왜냐하면 나는 당신에게 관심이 있었기 때문입니다.
But now, it's totally not like that.
그런데 지금은 전혀 그렇지 않습니다.
Now you're just a fellow crew member.
이제 당신은 단지 동료 승무원일 뿐입니다.
Okay, now it's your turn to talk.
자, 이제 당신이 말할 차례입니다.
About Jeong-suk.
정숙에 대해서.
I…
나…
I flunked the mock exam.
모의고사를 망쳤어요.
I heard.
들었어.
I really wanted to show Dad.
아빠한테 꼭 보여주고 싶었어요.
That I chose art school not because I couldn't go to med school.
내가 미술학원을 선택한 이유 내가 의과대학에 갈 수 없었기 때문이 아니다.
I wanted to prove that.
나는 그것을 증명하고 싶었습니다.
I'm so annoyed.
정말 짜증이 나요.
You should be studying for yourself.
스스로 공부해야 합니다.
Not to rebel against someone.
누군가에게 반항하는 것이 아닙니다.
Mom.
엄마.
That was so cliché.
너무 진부했어요.
No way.
안 돼요.
I'd rather have you yell at me for failing the exam.
차라리 네가 나한테 소리 지르면 좋겠어 시험에 실패해서.
How can I yell at you guys after giving you all that stress?
내가 어떻게 너희들에게 소리를 지르겠는가? 그 스트레스를 다 주고 나면?
Resolving these situations
이러한 상황을 해결하기
won't be easy.
쉽지 않을 것입니다.
But I'll resolve it in the most peaceful way possible.
하지만 내가 해결해줄게 가능한 가장 평화로운 방법으로.
So that you two and I will suffer the least amount of damage possible.
너와 내가 고통받도록 가능한 최소한의 피해.
I saw it on TV,
TV에서 봤는데,
but you raised me way too freely.
하지만 당신은 나를 너무 자유롭게 키웠어요.
Are you criticizing me by saying the way I raised you was wrong?
이런 말로 나를 비난하는 건가요? 내가 널 키운 방식이 틀렸어?
Look at you.
당신을보세요.
You're really not holding back now that you're all grown-up, are you?
너 정말 참지 못하는구나 이제 너희도 다 컸구나, 그렇지?
Thankfully, Dad was the complete opposite,
다행히 아빠는 정반대였지만,
so I ended up being only moderately spoiled.
그래서 난 결국 이렇게 됐어 적당히 버릇이 생겼습니다.
If not, I might've become a complete delinquent.
그렇지 않았다면 나는 이렇게 됐을지도 모른다. 완전 불량자.
A delinquent?
체납자?
Jeez.
이런.
I…
나는…
wanted my kids to be a little immature as they grew up.
내 아이들을 원했어 자라면서 조금 미성숙해지려고요.
I would always be there when you came home,
나는 항상 거기에있을 것입니다 당신이 집에 왔을 때,
and if you wanted something, you'd badger me for it.
그리고 당신이 뭔가를 원했다면, 당신은 그것 때문에 나에게 오소리를 할 것입니다.
I never got a chance to be like that.
나는 그렇게 될 기회가 없었습니다.
So simply put, the way I raised you was totally intentional.
그러니까 간단히 말해서 내가 널 키운 방식은 전적으로 의도적이었습니다.
Then you achieved your goal.
그러면 당신은 목표를 달성했습니다.
Of course. Look, I raised you freely,
물론. 보세요, 내가 당신을 자유롭게 키웠어요.
and that helped you find your own path.
그리고 그것은 당신이 자신의 길을 찾는 데 도움이 되었습니다.
That is true.
그것은 사실이다.
But I still don't understand.
하지만 아직도 이해가 안 돼요.
I wonder who you take after to draw so well?
누구를 따를지 궁금해 그렇게 잘 그릴까?
This patient was admitted to our hospital for colon cancer surgery.
이 환자분은 저희 병원에 입원하셨습니다. 대장암 수술을 위해.
The primary cause we're looking at is old age.
주요 원인 우리가 보고 있는 것은 노년기입니다.
And based on our investigation, given the patient's old age,
그리고 우리가 조사한 바에 따르면, 환자의 나이를 고려하여
the eating habits that had continued until now
식습관 그게 지금까지 계속됐어.
were extremely lacking in dietary fiber.
식이섬유가 매우 부족했습니다.
The patient also consumed a lot of foods
환자도 음식을 많이 먹었다.
that were high in fat as well as a lot of refined and processed foods.
지방도 많고 양도 많았어요 정제된 식품과 가공식품.
So we are looking at that as the cause.
그래서 우리는 그것을 원인으로 보고 있습니다.
-Where on earth-- -Don't say that!
-대체 어디-- - 그런 말 하지 마세요!
I'm not saying you should coddle him.
나는 당신이 그를 애지중지해야 한다고 말하는 것이 아닙니다.
Just don't trample all over him.
그 사람 전체를 짓밟지 마세요.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
When I was on night duty in the ER as a first-year,
내가 응급실에서 야간 근무를 했을 때 1학년으로서,
three patients from a car crash came in at the same time.
교통사고로 인한 환자 3명 동시에 들어왔습니다.
All of their vitals were unstable, and they were all gushing out blood.
모든 바이탈이 불안정했고, 그리고 그들은 모두 피를 흘리고 있었습니다.
It was an extremely critical situation, but we didn't have many doctors.
매우 위급한 상황이었는데, 하지만 우리에겐 의사가 많지 않았어요.
I thought I would have to declare all of them dead at that rate.
선언해야 한다고 생각했어요 그 속도로 모두 죽었어.
But thankfully two of them received surgery in time and survived.
하지만 다행스럽게도 그 중 두 명은 제때에 수술을 받고 살아 남았습니다.
What about the other one?
다른 하나는 어떻습니까?
There were only two options in my head.
내 머리 속에는 두 가지 선택밖에 없었다.
One was to wait for a professor who could perform surgery.
하나는 교수를 기다리는 것이었습니다 수술을 할 수 있는 사람.
The other was to transfer them.
다른 하나는 그것들을 옮기는 것이었습니다.
I decided to transfer them to a different hospital.
나는 그들을 옮기기로 결정했다 다른 병원으로.
But during the transfer,
하지만 이적 과정에서
the patient went into cardiac arrest and was pronounced DOA.
환자는 심정지 상태에 빠졌다 DOA로 발음되었습니다.
If I had waited, wouldn't the patient have received surgery?
내가 기다렸다면 환자는 그렇지 않았을까? 수술을 받았나요?
Then wouldn't the patient have lived?
그렇다면 환자는 살 수 없었을까요?
Those were some of the thoughts I had.
그것은 내가 가지고 있던 생각 중 일부였습니다.
That's when I realized.
그때 나는 깨달았다.
That a doctor's judgment
그건 의사의 판단
determines whether a patient will live or die.
환자인지 여부를 결정합니다. 살거나 죽을 것입니다.
Jung-min.
정민.
The fact is that the patient died. There's no denying that.
사실은 환자가 사망했다는 것입니다. 그것을 부인할 수는 없습니다.
Yes.
예.
If you want to be a good doctor, you can't avoid this situation.
좋은 의사가 되고 싶다면, 이 상황을 피할 수는 없습니다.
If you want to protest, then do so.
항의하고 싶으면 그렇게 하세요.
If you made a mistake, admit it and ask for forgiveness.
실수를 했다면, 인정하고 용서를 구하세요.
Don't forget your mistake and learn from it.
실수를 잊지 마세요 그리고 그것으로부터 배우세요.
So that you can make the right judgments.
그래야 올바른 판단을 내릴 수 있습니다.
So that you can help even more people.
그래야 더 많은 사람들에게 도움을 줄 수 있습니다.
That's how we all become doctors.
그것이 우리 모두가 의사가 되는 방법이다.
Okay.
좋아요.
I don't know if you'll agree with me on this,
모르겠어요 당신이 내 말에 동의한다면,
but you definitely…
하지만 당신은 확실히…
have sides to you that are better than me.
당신에겐 나보다 나은 면이 있어요.
Are you okay?
괜찮으세요?
No.
아니요.
If I could,
내가 할 수 있다면,
I want to just disappear.
그냥 사라지고 싶어요.
As you already know,
이미 알고 있듯이,
I'm not great with words.
나는 말에 능숙하지 않다.
And…
그리고…
there are no words right now that will make you feel better.
지금은 말이 없다 그러면 기분이 좋아질 것입니다.
But I can promise you this.
하지만 이건 약속할 수 있어요.
Until you find a way to get back on your feet,
방법을 찾을 때까지 다시 일어설 수 있도록,
I'll stay by your side
난 네 곁에 있을게
if you allow me to.
당신이 허락한다면.
Her family is threatening to sue.
그녀의 가족은 고소하겠다고 위협하고 있습니다.
The hospital will respond accordingly,
병원에서는 이에 대해 답변해 드리겠습니다.
but since Jung-min was the one who discharged her,
근데 정민이였으니까 누가 그녀를 퇴원시켰는지,
the family is finding fault with that.
가족은 그것에 대해 결점을 찾고 있습니다.
Jung-min needs to try to make an effort to come to an agreement.
정민이는 노력해야 해 합의를 하려고요.
It may seem unfair in your position, but what can be done?
자신의 입장에서는 불공평해 보일 수도 있지만, 하지만 무엇을 할 수 있습니까?
It'd be best to settle things before this situation grows any bigger.
문제를 해결하는 것이 가장 좋을 것입니다. 이 사태가 더 커지기 전에.
I fully understand what you are saying.
나는 당신이 말하는 것을 완전히 이해합니다.
But I still think this situation needs to be looked into more carefully.
하지만 아직은 이런 상황이 필요하다고 생각해요 좀 더 주의 깊게 살펴보기로 한다.
Professor Seo In-ho
서인호 교수
is trying to pin this medical accident on our department.
이 의료사고를 고정하려고 합니다 우리 부서에.
Since this involves his son,
이 사건은 그의 아들과 관련이 있기 때문에,
he's dead set on making sure our department takes the fall for it.
그 사람은 확실히 할 생각이 없어 우리 부서는 그 일을 맡습니다.
Jeez, you didn't know?
이런, 몰랐어?
Professor Seo?
서 교수님?
He's brazenly trying to force a lie on everyone.
그는 뻔뻔스럽게 노력하고 있어요 모든 사람에게 거짓말을 강요합니다.
That patient
그 환자
was your patient, Professor Choi.
환자분이셨어요, 최교수님.
Defend yourself.
자신을 방어하세요.
Otherwise, you might end up on the chopping block.
그렇지 않으면 결국 끝날 수도 있습니다. 도마 위에.
Professor Kim.
김 교수님.
Can't eat, right?
먹을 수 없어요, 그렇죠?
I guess not.
나는 아닌 것 같아요.
You were due for a checkup, you know.
당신은 건강검진을 받기로 되어 있었습니다.
Right.
오른쪽.
I had some medication left, so I forgot.
약이 남아서 깜빡했어요.
-I should go. -You have some left,
-가야겠어. - 좀 남았는데,
which means you forgot to take them.
이는 당신이 그것을 가져가는 것을 잊었다는 것을 의미합니다.
That's not true.
그것은 사실이 아닙니다.
The one thing I do for sure is take my medication regularly.
내가 확실히 하는 한 가지는 정기적으로 약을 복용하는 것입니다.
Are you going to keep lying?
계속 거짓말할 거예요?
Actually, I forgot a couple of times and didn't take them.
사실 몇 번이나 잊어버렸어 그리고 그것들을 가져가지 않았습니다.
You're not eating or taking your medication.
당신은 식사를하지 않습니다 아니면 약을 복용하든가.
This won't do. I'll wait until you finish your meal.
이건 안 돼요. 당신이 식사를 마칠 때까지 기다릴게요.
There's no need for that, Professor.
그럴 필요는 없습니다, 교수님.
Dr. Cha.
차 박사.
Take just half of the energy you use on others and use it for yourself.
사용하는 에너지의 절반만 가져가세요 다른 사람에게 사용하고 자신을 위해 사용하십시오.
If you continue to neglect taking care of yourself,
계속 방치한다면 자신을 돌보고,
something really bad may happen.
정말 나쁜 일이 일어날 수도 있어요.
I have the right to nag you.
나한테는 잔소리할 권리가 있다.
Of course. I'll take my medication regularly starting now.
물론. 약을 먹을게요 이제부터 정기적으로.
And I'll eat well too.
그리고 나도 잘 먹을게요.
Thank you for worrying about me.
걱정해주셔서 감사합니다.
Professor Seo.
서 교수님.
I heard you were blaming our department for the cancer patient.
우리 부서를 비난한다고 들었는데 암환자를 위해.
The patient was admitted and discharged by Family Medicine,
환자가 입원했습니다 가정의학과에서 퇴원했고,
so you should take responsibility if something occurs.
그러니 책임을 져야지 무슨 일이 생기면.
How is that our department's responsibility?
어때요? 우리 부서의 책임인가?
We requested a consultation,
저희가 상담을 요청했는데,
and your department took one look and discharged her right away.
그리고 당신 부서가 한 번 살펴봤죠 그리고 바로 퇴원시켰습니다.
We did?
우리가 그랬나요?
Hey, Seo In-ho!
안녕하세요, 서인호님!
I know that your resident called my resident
나는 당신의 거주자를 알고 내 주민에게 전화했어
confirming that you gave the okay for the patient's discharge.
당신이 괜찮다고 확인하는 것 환자의 퇴원을 위해.
Do you really not know that?
정말 그걸 모르시나요?
She was discharged before the official answer was closed.
그녀는 퇴원했다 공식적인 답변이 종료되기 전에.
Even if that was the case, the official decision to discharge
그랬다고 해도, 공식적인 해고 결정
is made by the department that admitted her.
부서에서 만들어요 그것은 그녀를 인정했습니다.
Technically, isn't she a patient from your department?
엄밀히 말하면 그 사람은 환자 아닌가요? 당신 부서에서요?
That's why we asked for a consultation, so your resident looked into her,
그래서 상담을 요청했는데, 그래서 당신의 주민이 그녀를 조사했고,
and you even gave the okay too.
그리고 너도 괜찮다고 했어.
If the surgery department says so,
외과에서 그렇게 말하면
there's no reason for us not to discharge her.
우리에겐 이유가 없어 그녀를 해고하지 말라고.
My resident seems to have made some mistakes.
내 주민이 보인다 몇 가지 실수를 저질렀다는 것입니다.
In that regard, I'll give him a warning.
그런 점에서 나는 그에게 경고를 하겠다.
Giving him a warning won't solve the issue here, will it?
그에게 경고를 하는 것 여기서는 문제가 해결되지 않을 텐데요, 그렇죠?
I'm not sure.
잘 모르겠습니다.
If the records were left in detail,
기록이 자세하게 남아 있었다면,
and he carried out all the necessary duties,
그리고 그는 수행했다 필요한 모든 의무,
then that means the patient neglected his warning and went home.
그렇다면 그것은 환자를 의미합니다 그의 경고를 무시하고 집으로 돌아갔습니다.
Regarding the peritonitis, we actively and aggressively performed surgery,
복막염에 대해 우리는 적극적으로 공격적으로 수술을 진행했고,
but it did not go well.
하지만 잘 안 됐어요.
So it's hard to say it's the hospital's fault.
그래서 말하기가 어렵습니다. 그건 병원 잘못이에요.
Regardless, the fact that my department is involved in this incident offends me.
어쨌든 내가 속한 부서는 이 사건에 연루되어 있어 기분이 상합니다.
Of course, Family Medicine is involved.
물론 가정의학과도 관련이 있습니다.
Medical accidents can occur regardless of someone's intention or wrongdoing.
의료사고는 관계없이 발생할 수 있습니다. 누군가의 의도나 잘못.
But someone always has to be held accountable.
하지만 누군가는 항상 책임을 져야 합니다.
So we need to officially decide who is responsible.
그러니 우리는 공식적으로 결정해야 합니다 책임이 있는 사람.
If my department suffers because of this--
이로 인해 우리 부서가 어려움을 겪는다면--
If the patient was admitted after seeing Family Medicine--
환자가 입원한 경우 가정의학과를 본 후--
Regardless,
그럼에도 불구하고,
please take back what you said
당신이 한 말을 취소해주세요
about how Family Medicine should be held responsible.
가정의학 방법에 대해 책임을 져야 합니다.
-What? -I'll take it that you'll do as I asked.
-무엇? -부탁한 대로 하도록 하겠습니다.
You came again.
당신은 다시 왔습니다.
Actually,
실제로,
I came because I have something to tell you both.
내가 온 이유는 두 분 모두에게 말씀드릴 게 있습니다.
The resident who discharged her came before too.
그녀를 퇴원시킨 주민 전에도 왔어.
He left after crying on his knees.
그는 무릎을 꿇고 울면서 떠났다.
But doing that won't bring our child back.
하지만 그렇게 한다고 해서 우리 아이가 다시 돌아올 수는 없습니다.
I want to explain to you why your daughter died.
나는 당신에게 설명하고 싶습니다 왜 당신 딸이 죽었나요?
I don't want to hear it, so please leave.
듣기 싫으니 나가주세요.
Why are you here at this hour out of the blue?
이 시간에 왜 여기 있어요? 갑자기?
Is something wrong?
뭔가 문제가 있나요?
What could be wrong?
무엇이 잘못되었을 수 있나요?
I just came to sleep over.
방금 자러 왔어요.
Are you sure nothing is wrong?
아무 문제가 없다고 확신하시나요?
I'm telling you, nothing's wrong.
내가 말하는데, 아무 문제도 없어.
I came here after the group dinner because I missed you so much.
단체 저녁 식사 후에 여기 왔어요 왜냐하면 나는 당신을 너무 그리워했기 때문입니다.
MS. OH DEOK-RYE
MS. 오덕례
Yes, Ms. Oh.
네, 오 선생님.
It's been a while.
오랜만이에요.
To what do I owe this pleasure?
내가 이 기쁨을 누리고 있는 이유는 무엇입니까?
I just called to see how things are.
방금 상황이 어떤지 알아보려고 전화했어요.
I was using the cosmetics you gave me,
주신 화장품을 사용하고 있었는데,
and I wondered if you were well,
그리고 당신은 잘 지내는지 궁금했어요.
and how you feel after your surgery.
그리고 수술 후 기분이 어떤지.
I see.
알겠어요.
Gosh, thanks to you, I'm doing so well.
맙소사, 덕분에 너무 잘 지내고 있어요.
There's nothing wrong with In-ho or Jeong-suk, right?
인호는 아무 잘못 없어 아니면 정숙이 맞죠?
In truth, Jeong-suk
사실 정숙이는
looked so down the last time I saw her that it's been bothering me.
지난번에 그녀를 봤을 때 정말 우울해 보였어 그것이 나를 괴롭히고 있다는 것입니다.
Gosh.
이런.
The work at the hospital is hard.
병원 일은 힘들어요.
Right.
오른쪽.
As a matter of fact, there was a place I wanted to go with you.
사실 그런 곳이 있었거든요 나는 당신과 함께 가고 싶었습니다.
Do you have time today?
오늘 시간 있어요?
Today?
오늘?
This is a very famous Korean medical clinic.
이것은 매우 유명한 것입니다. 한의원.
After taking the medicine I got here,
약을 먹고 여기까지 왔습니다.
I regained my strength.
나는 힘을 되찾았습니다.
Ms. Oh Deok-rye.
오덕례 선생님.
-Yes.
-예.
PROFESSOR PARK HO-WON I RECEIVED YOUR INVESTMENT
박호원 교수 나는 당신의 투자를 받았습니다
MAY THERE BE A PROSPEROUS FUTURE FOR US
우리에게 번영하는 미래가 있을지도 모릅니다
Your pulse is irregular.
맥박이 불규칙합니다.
Your blood density as it flows into your blood vessels is low,
흐르는 혈액 밀도 혈관 속으로 들어가는 농도가 낮습니다.
and it doesn't flow smoothly either.
그리고 원활하게 흐르지도 않습니다.
In particular, the pulse tied to your liver and stomach functions
특히, 펄스 묶음 간 및 위장 기능에
have declined a lot.
많이 거절했습니다.
You have inflammation inside your body as well.
염증이 있어요 몸 안에서도 마찬가지다.
Am I that unwell?
내가 그렇게 몸이 안 좋은 걸까?
You're lucky to be alive and moving.
당신은 살아서 움직이는 것이 행운입니다.
You probably haven't been able to sleep and have a hard time eating.
아마 잠을 못 이루셨을 거예요 그리고 먹기 힘들어요.
Medicine is one thing, but you should begin treatment right away.
의학은 한 가지이다. 하지만 즉시 치료를 시작해야 합니다.
VERITY KOREAN MEDICAL CLINIC
베리티한의원
That doctor is supposed to be really talented.
그 의사가 설마 정말 재능이 있는 것 같아요.
How strange.
정말 이상해요.
Don't be concerned.
걱정하지 마세요.
It's just because I'm old.
단지 내가 늙었기 때문일 뿐입니다.
I'll buy you a delicious dinner too. What would you like to eat?
나도 맛있는 저녁 사줄게. 무엇을 드시겠어요?
-You want to have dinner? -Yes.
-저녁 먹을래? -예.
Ms. Kwak.
곽씨.
Do you not know what today is?
오늘이 무슨 날인지 모르시나요?
What day is it today?
오늘은 무슨 날인가요?
It's not my birthday…
내 생일은 아닌데…
What could it be?
그것은 무엇일까요?
Do you have redder apples?
더 빨간 사과 있나요?
Of course. Are you preparing for a memorial service?
물론. 준비하고 있나요? 추도식으로?
Yes.
예.
Who is it for?
누구를 위한 것인가요?
My father-in-law.
나의 시아버지.
Goodness, in this day and age?
세상에, 요즘 시대에?
You're a daughter-in-law that's one in a million.
당신은 며느리입니다 그것은 백만 분의 일입니다.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
-Did you tell her to come? -No.
- 오라고 했어? -아니요.
I'm not that shameless.
저는 그렇게 뻔뻔한 사람이 아닙니다.
How can I ask her to prepare for my father's memorial service?
어떻게 그녀에게 준비를 부탁할 수 있나요? 아버지 제사를 위해?
If she came on her own
만약 그녀가 스스로 왔더라면
to prepare all of this for her father-in-law,
이 모든 것을 준비하기 위해 시아버지를 위해서,
doesn't that mean she forgives you?
그 말은 그 사람이 당신을 용서했다는 뜻 아닌가요?
Isn't this some kind of silent message
이건 일종의 무언의 메시지가 아닌가?
that she's done with what she was doing and coming back to the family?
그 사람이 하던 일이 끝났다고 그리고 가족에게로 돌아오나요?
That would be a relief.
그러면 안심이 될 것입니다.
Let's go help her prepare the food today.
오늘 그녀가 음식 준비하는 것을 도와주러 가자.
But I just got my nails done.
그런데 방금 손톱을 다듬었어요.
Please cooperate this time too!
이번에도 협력해주세요!
In her eyes, you're an accomplice.
그녀의 눈에는 당신이 공범입니다.
Why am I an accomplice?
내가 왜 공범입니까?
You're the one who cheated, not me.
속인 건 내가 아니라 당신이에요.
Good job on saying something so blasphemous
뭔가 말하길 잘했어 너무 신성모독적이야
on the anniversary of your father's death.
네 아버지의 기일에.
It'll be lucky if your father doesn't get indigestion
운이 좋을 거야 아버지가 소화불량에 걸리지 않는다면
after eating the food today.
오늘 밥을 먹은 후.
Jeong-suk.
정숙.
Is there anything I can help with?
제가 도와드릴 게 있나요?
Don't cut the radish too small for the bean sprout soup.
무를 너무 작게 자르지 마세요 콩나물국을 위해.
Cut it long like this, like a bean sprout.
콩나물처럼 이렇게 길게 잘라주세요.
-Like this? -Yes.
-이와 같이? -예.
The same goes for the chive and scallion pancakes.
부추도 마찬가지 그리고 파 팬케이크.
You can't cut the food that will be offered into short pieces.
음식을 자를 수는 없어요 짧은 조각으로 제공됩니다.
Jeez, but you already know all this so well.
이런, 하지만 당신은 이미 알고 있어요 이 모든 것이 너무 좋습니다.
What's the point of me knowing?
내가 아는 게 무슨 소용이 있겠어?
I can't do this forever.
나는 이것을 영원히 할 수 없습니다.
What?
무엇?
Honey, can I make them like this?
여보, 이렇게 만들어도 될까요?
Watch carefully. Not in the middle, but at the one-third point.
주의 깊게 관찰하세요. 중간은 아니고, 하지만 3분의 1 지점에서요.
So the red side of the crab meat can be seen from the front.
그래서 게살의 붉은색 부분이 정면에서 볼 수 있습니다.
Okay.
좋아요.
Then a yellow radish.
그런 다음 노란 무.
The same goes for the chives.
부추도 마찬가지입니다.
Make the broader side show from the front, not the narrower side.
정면에서 보면 측면이 더 넓어보이고, 좁은 쪽이 아닙니다.
-I see.
-알겠어요.
Mushrooms as well.
버섯도요.
And next goes the ham. That way the colors are pretty like this.
그리고 다음은 햄입니다. 그래서 색깔이 이렇게 이쁘네요.
And then at the end, one last piece of red crab meat.
그리고 마지막에는, 마지막 붉은 게살 한 조각.
Memorial services are all about care.
추도식은 배려에 관한 것입니다.
You need to do it like this so it looks good,
이렇게해야합니다 그래서 좋아 보이는데,
and so the egg, flour, and water will stick properly and make it cook well.
그래서 계란, 밀가루, 물이 제대로 붙어서 잘 익을 거예요.
-Use this one as an example and follow it. -Okay.
- 예시를 들어보고 따라해보세요. -좋아요.
It's a mere formality, so don't put too much effort in.
그냥 형식적인거지만 그러니 너무 많은 노력을 기울이지 마세요.
What are you doing?
뭐하는 거야?
What?
무엇?
I think
내 생각엔
we should stop with the memorial service.
추모식은 그만둬야 해요.
We should just gather as a family to pray and share a meal
그냥 가족끼리 모여야지 기도하고 식사를 나누다
on this day from now on.
지금부터 오늘.
Why all of a sudden?
왜 갑자기?
We're Christians,
우리는 기독교인입니다.
so your father must have passed on to heaven.
그러니 네 아버지가 그러셨을 거야 천국으로 넘어갔습니다.
So what is the point of this?
그렇다면 이것의 요점은 무엇입니까?
And it isn't right. It's too much work on Jeong-suk's part.
그리고 그것은 옳지 않습니다. 정숙 씨의 일이 너무 많아요.
Just look at today.
오늘만 보세요.
She just stood in the kitchen all day and worked so hard.
그녀는 하루종일 부엌에만 서 있었어 그리고 정말 열심히 일했어요.
You can do it next year onwards, Mother.
내년부터 해도 됩니다, 어머니.
As you already know, I'm a bad cook.
당신도 이미 알고 있듯이, 나는 서투른 요리사입니다.
Before you married into the family, my mother-in-law took care of things.
가족과 결혼하기 전에, 시어머니가 모든 일을 처리하셨다.
Ever since you came, you took care of everything so well.
당신이 온 이후로, 당신은 모든 일을 아주 잘 처리해 주었습니다.
So I never had the time to learn to cook.
그래서 요리를 배울 시간이 없었어요.
You can learn now.
지금 배울 수 있습니다.
-I can help too. -Come on!
-나도 도울 수 있어요. -어서 해봐요!
I'm saying I don't want to do this anymore!
내 말은 더 이상 이러고 싶지 않아요!
I don't understand why you want to stop doing Father's memorial service.
왜 당신이 원하는지 이해가 안 돼요 아버지 제사를 중단하려고요.
Grandma, do you have a boyfriend?
할머니, 남자친구 있어요?
The thing is…
문제는…
Yes, I have a person I'm seeing.
네, 만나는 사람이 있어요.
I don't know how things will end up with him,
모르겠어요 그 사람의 결말은 어떻게 될지,
so continuing to hold memorial services for your father
그래서 계속 잡고 있다 아버지를 위한 추도식
does make me uncomfortable.
나를 불편하게 만든다.
So you're saying you have a boyfriend?
그럼 남자친구가 있다는 말씀이신가요?
Do you have marriage in mind?
결혼을 염두에 두고 있나요?
Why?
왜?
Is there a reason I can't?
내가 할 수 없는 이유가 있나요?
I'm single.
나는 독신이다.
To think she has a boyfriend at that age.
그 나이에 남자친구가 있다고 생각하면.
This is absurd.
이것은 터무니없는 일입니다.
I don't know if you're grasping this,
이 내용을 이해하고 계신지 모르겠습니다.
but you're going to get yourself a new father-in-law.
하지만 너는 너 자신을 얻을거야 새로운 시아버지.
Head to your room. I'll do it alone.
방으로 가세요. 나 혼자 할게.
No, I was too inattentive with the chores. I'll help out the best I can from now on.
아니요, 집안일에 너무 부주의했습니다. 이제부터 최선을 다해 도와드리겠습니다.
Sure, learning this will be good for you.
물론, 이것을 배우면 당신에게 도움이 될 것입니다.
Since I won't be here anymore.
왜냐하면 나는 더 이상 여기에 없을 것이기 때문이다.
What is that supposed to mean?
그게 무슨 뜻일까요?
This is the last memorial service I'll prepare.
이것이 마지막 추모식이다 내가 준비할게.
Let's…
하자…
get a divorce.
이혼하세요.
Divorce?
이혼?
I saw your car in the hospital parking lot.
나는 당신의 차를 보았다 병원 주차장에서.
You had the disability sticker I received,
제가 받은 장애 스티커를 갖고 계셨는데요,
and you parked your car right in front of the hospital entrance
그리고 넌 차를 주차했어 병원 입구 바로 앞
where the accessible parking is.
접근 가능한 주차장이 있는 곳.
DRIVER WITH DISABILITY
장애가 있는 운전자
ACCESSIBLE PARKING
접근 가능한 주차
You put my disability sticker on your car…
내 장애 스티커를 차에 붙이셨군요…
and drove around Seung-hi.
그리고 승희 주변을 운전했습니다.
The thought of that made me laugh.
그런 생각이 나를 웃게 만들었습니다.
The fact that I lived my life
인생을 살았다는 사실
caring for and putting this lousy guy on a pedestal
돌보고 보살핌 받침대 위의 이 형편없는 남자
made me feel so pathetic and stupid.
나를 너무 한심하고 바보처럼 느끼게 만들었습니다.
And then suddenly,
그러더니 갑자기,
I had this thought.
이런 생각이 들었습니다.
All of this isn't just your fault.
이 모든 것은 단지 당신의 잘못이 아닙니다.
Your mother failed to teach you right from wrong.
당신의 어머니는 실패했습니다 옳고 그름을 가르치기 위해.
And I was so permissive in every single regard.
저는 너무 관대했어요 모든 면에서.
Our responsibility in this isn't any less.
이에 대한 우리의 책임은 결코 적지 않습니다.
I'd like to make a report.
보고서를 작성하고 싶습니다.
Someone is illegally parked in an accessible parking spot.
누군가 불법주차를 하고 있어요 접근 가능한 주차 장소에 있습니다.
The driver has a disability sticker on his car.
운전자는 그의 차에 붙어 있는 장애 스티커.
But he's nondisabled.
하지만 그 사람은 비장애인이에요.
Yes.
예.
I've made my decision.
나는 결정을 내렸다.
I think the time has come
이제 때가 된 것 같아
when it'll be okay if we're just Jung-min and I-rang's parents.
정민이만 있으면 언제쯤 괜찮을까 그리고 이랑의 부모님.
As the father of my children, I can let things slide.
내 아이들의 아버지로서, 나는 일을 미끄러지게 할 수 있습니다.
But…
하지만…
as my husband,
내 남편으로서,
you no longer…
너는 더 이상…
hold any meaning to me.
나에게 어떤 의미라도 부여해주세요.
I don't want to hate you anymore.
나는 더 이상 당신을 미워하고 싶지 않습니다.
I just don't feel the need to hate you anymore.
나는 단지 필요성을 느끼지 않는다. 당신을 더 이상 미워하지 않기 위해.
It's already over…
이미 끝났어…
between the two of us.
우리 둘 사이.
I want to be liberated from this hell.
나는 이 지옥에서 해방되고 싶다.
Let's split up.
헤어지자.
Let's get a divorce.
이혼하자
Don't put on an act.
행동을 취하지 마십시오.
Get up.
일어나세요.
Get up!
일어나세요!
Honey.
꿀.
Honey, open your eyes. Come on.
여보, 눈을 떠보세요. 어서 해봐요.
In-ho!
인호!
What's with you?
당신은 무엇입니까?
In-ho, open your eyes.
인호야, 눈을 떠라.
Honey!
꿀!
Honey, please wake up!
여보, 일어나주세요!
I don't want to get a divorce.
나는 이혼하고 싶지 않습니다.
Use this opportunity to play the role of a good husband.
이 기회를 활용하세요 좋은 남편의 역할을 하려고요.
Mr. Seo In-ho. It's already too late.
서인호 선생님. 이미 너무 늦었어요.
Mom, are you in pain? What's wrong?
엄마, 많이 아프세요? 무슨 일이야?
Don't let my mom know what's going on between us for now.
엄마에게 알리지 마세요 지금 우리 사이에 무슨 일이 벌어지고 있는 걸까요.
The professor in charge of Grandma.
할머니를 담당하는 교수님.
It's Professor Choi Seung-hi.
최승희 교수님입니다.
Did you accept my mother as your patient on purpose?
저희 어머니를 받아주셨나요? 일부러 환자로 삼으신 겁니까?
Isn't that up to you?
그건 당신에게 달려 있지 않나요?
Subtitle translation by: Yoon-ji Chi
자막번역 : 지윤지